Now תמיד *Tamid*, which picks up on כ"ח עמוד ב' *kaf-chet amud
bet*, if you turn a few pages, there is actually, believe it
or not, גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on this. Let me say a little
bit about what this מסכת *masechet* is. First of all, the entire
מסכת *masechet* is a, in principle, it's a discussion about how the
קרבן תמיד *korban tamid* was brought every morning. But before it gets
up to how the קרבן תמיד *korban tamid* was brought every morning,
it tells us basically what happened in the early morning in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, pretty much from the time of
the watches at night till the opening of the gates and until
the תרומת הדשן *terumas hadeshen* and all of like the early stuff
to get it up and running through the קרבן תמיד *korban tamid*.
So I think for most of us we're saying wow, that's interesting,
good, finally get to find out what actually happened.
It's almost seven and a half years in the ש"ס *Shas*.
Exactly. Let me read to you here, I printed this out here.
This is from the רמב"ם'ס *Rambam's* פירוש המשנה Peirush HaMishnah, *Peirush HaMishnah*
in his introduction to פירוש המשנה *Peirush HaMishnah* in the beginning of
זרעים *Zeraim*. So at the end of that he discusses what the
whole division of מסכתות *masechtos* is. The one that just looks like
a straight column here.
At the end of that he discusses what the order of the
מסכתות *masechtos* is in a סדר *seder*. It doesn't say that it
goes on size. He tries to make a logical order. No, no,
no, it's flip-sides, it's two sides of a page. Okay, so anyway
he says here in the last column, he says like this, he
speaks about what the order of things are.
ואחר כריתות מעילה *Ve'achar Kerisos Meilah*. No, it says the word כריתות
*Kerisos* at the beginning of a line, it's the last column about
ten lines from the bottom. Okay, after כריתות *Kerisos* comes מעילה *Meilah*,
לפי שדברים שחייבים עליהם מעילה קלים מדברים שחייבים עליהם חטאת *lefi shedevarim
shechayavim aleihem meilah kalim midevarim shechayavim aleihem chatas*. Okay, so that's an
interesting discussion. Why? Because since we're talking about כריתות *Kerisos*, which is
things you have to bring a חטאת *chatas* for, then we're going
to talk about מעילה *Meilah*, which the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says somehow
is lighter than the things that you bring a חטאת *chatas*. I
assume he means that there's not a חייב כרת *chayav kares* for
the act of
מעילה *meilah*. It's actually debated in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, some say
מזיד *meizid* in מעילה *meilah* is מיתה בידי שמים *misah biyedei shamayim*.
Anyway, but for us moving on, ואחר מעילה מסכת תמיד *Ve'achar meilah
masechet Tamid*, that's 29, because this is the real order, okay, comes
תמיד *Tamid*, why? והאחר אותה *vehe'acher osah*, and why does it have
תמיד *Tamid* last? לפי שאין בה דינים ולא איסור והיתר *lefi she'ein
bah dinim velo issur veheter*. There's no הלכה *halacha* discussion in it,
right? It's all descriptive. There's no discussion about what's forbidden, what's permissible,
it's all description. אלא סיפור *ella sippur*. It's just narrative, right? Descriptive.
היך היה תמיד קרב *heich hayah tamid karev*. How was it brought?
כדי שיהא נהוג תמיד *kedei sheyehei nahug tamid*. So we should know
when there's another בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* how we should
go ahead and bring the קרבן תמיד *korban tamid*. And once we're
here we'll read the rest. ואחר תמיד מדות *ve'achar Tamid Middos*, and
after that there is מדות *Middos*. ואין ענינה אלא סיפור מדת המקדש
Mikdash, וצורתה *ve'ein inyanah ella sippur middas Hamikdash vetzurah*. They are also
purely descriptive, no הלכה *halacha*, purely descriptive, what did the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* look like? והיך בניינו *veheich binyano*, how was
it constructed? והתועלת בכך *vehatoelet bekach*. So why do we have to
know this? שכשיבנה נשמור בו אותה צורה ואותו היחס *shekesheyibaneh nishmor bo
osah tzurah veoso hayachas*, that when it gets rebuilt we'll know how
to build it. כי הכל ה' עלי השכיל *ki hakol Hashem alai
hiskil*, as it says, כל ה' עלי השכיל *kol Hashem alai hiskil*.
Okay, and then finally it goes to קנים *Kinnim* and that was
just small so we just put it at the end. So anyway,
the important point you see he says here there's really no הלכה
*halacha*, it's all descriptive. Of course some הלכות *halachos* are referred to
and alluded to and implicit, but it's all basically descriptive. And the
other thing you'll see about תמיד *Tamid* and מדות *Middos* is almost
a complete absence of
names of תנאים *Tannaim*. It's almost all סתם *stam*. Okay, because it's
all descriptive and there's no discussions or debates, although you would have
thought even by descriptions different people would have had different memories or
different versions, but nevertheless it's practically all סתם *stam*. Yes?
This fits more for מדות *Middos* than תמיד *Tamid*, but the תנ"ך
*Tanakh* gives dimensions for the Temple. Yes. So wouldn't that be הלכה
*halacha*?
Yeah, but that's בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. ראשון *Beis HaMikdash Rishon*, בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash שני *Beis HaMikdash Sheni* looked differently.
So when we build the third Temple,
yeah we should really go by the פסוקים *pesukim* in יחזקאל *Yechezkel*,
not by מסכת מדות *masechet Middos*. That's a good point. I don't
know, I don't know. So anyway he passes those around, this is
for you to hold on and take back, you're going to want
this both when we do תמיד *Tamid* and מדות *Middos*. Okay, these
are nice little pictures of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash?
*Beis HaMikdash*. So does the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* say in these places
that we have to do לשמור בו אותה צורה ואותו היחס *lishmor
bo osah tzurah veoso hayachas*? Does that mean the third בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* has to be based a replica of the
second? That's what it sounds like, or like the same proportions or
something like that.
Yeah, it's not clear. And the problem is that יחזקאל *Yechezkel* draws
out a completely different description.
But מדות *Middos* is
a מדרש *midrash* and they say also that the proportions have to
come down from heaven. That's a מחלוקת *machlokes* about what we really
believe back then.
No, but this is based on
the משנה mishnah *mishnah*.
The משנה mishnah. *mishnah* is considered to be a very early משנה
mishnah, *mishnah*. Yes, yes, it's considered to be of a very early
layer.
So if it's an early משנה mishnah *mishnah*, it might the Temple
that הורדוס *Hordus* built might have actually had different dimensions.
No, not that early.
Okay, not pre-הורדוס *Hordus*. All right, so let's take a look, but
that's the next מסכת *masechet* which is מדות *Middos*, but even before...
But even in תמיד we're going to be talking about how things
happened, so I want you to have a picture of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So let's take a look. בשלושה מקומות הכהנים שומרים
בבית המקדש. Bishlosha mekomot hakohanim shomrim beveit hamikdash.
The כהנים kohanim would do their guarding and I'll talk about that
in a minute, their watch maybe, in three places in the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. בית אבטינס, Beit Avtinas, בית הניצוץ, Beit HaNitzotz, and
בית המוקד. Beit HaMoked.
So if you take a look here at the picture,
let's see, I guess if you take a look at the, yeah,
why don't you take a look at the one that's labeled? That's
easier because it actually has the labels. So you see that they
have here on the far right in the actual what?
The one that says המקדש השני HaMikdash HaSheni on the top. Okay,
in the far right on the bottom you have בית הניצוץ, Beit
HaNitzotz, right, the spark, בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, okay, there's some question
exactly which order they were in, some say בית המוקד Beit HaMoked
was further east. Anyway, and at the and here at the top
you have what was the other one? בית אבטינס. Beit Avtinas. בית
אבטינס, Beit Avtinas, does it not show this?
I'm looking at, yes it does.
The one on the, the first, the one on the left after
you know the middle of the page. The first one, it says
שער המים Shaar HaMayim on the top and underneath לשכת בית אבטינס.
Lishkat Beit Avtinas. Do you see that?
Oh, I'm sorry, it's on top.
You see, if you go halfway in the page, right, the black
line in the middle, on the left of the black line is
the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, right, which is like the social hall,
it basically didn't have the level of קדושה kedusha of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. To the right of the black line is the
actual עזרה, Azarah, okay? The top of the page, the left of
the page, the opening is east, the top of the page is
actually a little confusingly south. Okay, if you see that, right, east,
west, whatever. So anyway at the top of the page the south
you have בית אבטינס Beit Avtinas and on the bottom of the
page the north, both of these in the עזרה, Azarah, you have
the בית המוקד Beit HaMoked and the בית הניצוץ. Beit HaNitzotz. Now
that's where they would watch. Now if you see at the openings
there's a שער, shaar, there's a gate, right, at the, you know,
towards the, you know, away from, you know, because actually this would
be, these lines here would be steps, you could actually go up
and go in, right, through these gates. Do you see where it
says שער, shaar, the gate? Yes. So they would watch. Now, would
they actually watch at the gates themselves? No. They would if you
take a look at the for one minute turn to a few
pages forward to מידות Middot and you'll see the very beginning of
מידות, Middot, it's page sort of ל"ד lamed dalet here but there's
not, it's discontinuous.
Anyway, if you can turn to the beginning of מידות. Middot. Okay,
first משנה mishna starts exactly the same as our משנה. בשלושה מקומות
הכהנים שומרים בבית המקדש, Bishlosha mekomot hakohanim shomrim beveit hamikdash, בבית אבטינס
ובבית הניצוץ ובבית המוקד. beveit Avtinas uveveit haNitzotz uveveit haMoked. But then
it says והלויים בעשרים ואחד. vehalviyim be'esrim ve'echad. So the כהנים kohanim
were in three places, the לויים Leviyim were in twenty-one places. Okay,
and it says what were their places? חמישה על חמישה שערי הר
הבית, Chamisha al chamisha shaarei har habayit, five by the gates of
הר הבית, Har HaBayit, which would be like you know where the
כותל Kotel is is the wall around הר הבית, Har HaBayit, it's
not the actual wall of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash So they
would have five watches around the הר הבית Har HaBayit itself. ארבעה
על ארבע פינותיו, Arba'a al arba pinotav, four at not on the
gates of the הר הבית Har HaBayit but at the corners of
the wall, מתוכו, mitokho, on the inside. חמישה על חמישה שערי העזרה,
Chamisha al chamisha shaarei ha'azarah, five by the five gates of the
עזרה Azarah and four on the corners of the עזרה, Azarah, etcetera,
etcetera. Okay, so they would actually be watching at the, besides at
the base of הר הבית, Har HaBayit, at these gates. At these,
here there're seven, some say there are five, some say they watched
five of the seven, but they would be guarding at the gates
of these sort of, not vestibules but of these like rooms. So
where would the כהנים kohanim be? So as we're going to see
in a minute in the משנה, the כהנים kohanim would be on
the roof, okay? They'd be down there the guards at the gates
and the כהנים kohanim would be up at the roof, you know,
when you watch from the top of a wall. Okay, so that's
the three places כהנים, kohanim, twenty-one places לויים Leviyim around הר הבית
Har HaBayit and also around the עזרה. Azarah. Now, what is this
all about? The גמרא is going to say that there is a
מצוה mitzvah of כהנים kohanim and
לויים Leviyim to guard the המקדש, because it says a number of
places in the תורה, Torah, it says to אהרן, Aharon, you know,
I've given to you the לויים Leviyim to be שומר משמרת אהל
מועד, shomer mishmeret ohel moed, you know, to guard the protection of
the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, and speaks a number of times about
משה אהרן ובניו Moshe Aharon uvanav שומרים משמרת הקודש, shomrim mishmeret hakodesh,
right, they would guard the אהל מועד Ohel Moed and משה Moshe
was a לוי, Levi, not a כהן. Kohen. So from there we
learn that both כהנים kohanim and לויים, Leviyim, although obviously in different
roles, כהנים kohanim a little bit more inner or whatever, have this
idea of watching, guarding the מקדש. Mikdash. Now what is the purpose
of this? So if you look, this מפרש, mefaresh, by the way,
nobody calls this רש"י, Rashi, everybody calls this the מפרש, mefaresh, the
guy on the right here. He actually says it's a גזירת הכתוב
gezeirat hakatuv because actually logically you would think that God can protect
himself and you shouldn't and that actually it's a sense like we're
afraid things are going to be stolen and maybe that's like a
little undercutting of the honor. So if you look here at the
רש"י Rashi or whatever the מפרש mefaresh he says like this. It's
like... the end of the third of the third line from the
top. ובגמרא נפקא לן מקרא, Uvagemara nafka lan mikra, we learned from
a פסוק, pasuk, דבית המקדש צריך שימור, deveit hamikdash tzarich shimur, דאילו
לאו נפקא לן מקרא, de'ilu lav nafka lan mikra, had we not
learned it from a פסוק, pasuk, הוה אמינא דלא צריך שימור, hava
amina delo tzarich shimur, you don't want guards. דאין עניות במקום עשירות,
de'ein aniyut bemakom ashirut, which is a general principle, you don't want
to look poor in a place of wealth, right? And this is
a thing, and this is a sign of poverty. Now, really wealthy
people do protect their property, but the point being it's sort of,
it's maybe a little bit too petty. ואי גנבי כלי מקדש קנא
אחרין, ve'i ganvei klei mikdash kanya achrinei, because, you know, if you're
really wealthy, so things get stolen, I'll buy new. I'm not sure
any wealthy person acts that way, but anyway. בעוד הוה אמינא בחד
שומר סגי, be'od hava amina bechad shomer sagi, maybe just one. So
anyway, it's a פסוק pasuk because logically I would have said maybe
it's even counter some of the aesthetics or values of the מקדש.
Mikdash. The רמב"ם Rambam says the exact opposite. If you look on
the flip side of the page I handed out before with the
פירוש המשנה, not the diagram page. Here's the רמב"ם Rambam in פרק
ח Perek Chet of בית הבחירה. Beit HaBechirah. He says, שמירת המקדש
מצות עשה, Shemirat hamikdash mitzvat aseh, guarding the temple is a positive
מצוה. mitzvah. ואף על פי שאין שם פחד מאויב ולא מליסטים, Ve'af
al pi she'ein sham pachad me'oyev velo milistim, right? It's not because
of a fear of enemies or of robbers. שאין שמירתו אלא כבוד
לו, She'ein shemirato ella kavod lo, guarding it is honor to God.
Why? How's that honor? אינו דומה פלטורין שיש עליו שומרים לפלטורין שאין
עליו שומרים. Eino domeh paltorin sheyesh alav shomrim lepaltorin she'ein alav shomrim.
A castle with guards is not, is not the same as a
castle without guards. Okay, because you know, a normal way of kings
and castles is you have the whole, you know, whatever, changing of
the guards and the guards marching around and all that type of
a thing. Nobody says, "Oh my god, it's a big alarm system."
They actually say, "This is a way you show respect, is that
people are constantly there in a presence and a, and you know,
showing their sense of protecting and not even, not because of the
costliness of the gold that's used, but the sense of respect it
achieves." And then the רמב"ם Rambam says, just to finish, שמירה זו
כל הלילה, Shemirah zu kol halaylah, you do it all night. והשומרים
הם הכהנים והלויים, Vehashomrim hem hakohanim vehaleviyim, שנאמר, shene'emar, והחונים לפני המשכן
לפני אהל מועד קדמה, vehachonim lifnei hamishkan lifnei ohel mo'ed kedma, etc.,
כלומר אתם תהיו שומרים לו, kelomar atem tihyu shomrim lo, ושמרתם את
משמרת המשכן, veshetishmeru et mishmeret hamishkan, קהת Kehat
etc., משה אהרן ובניו. Moshe Aharon uvanav. הלכה ג, Halachah Gimmel, he
says, מצות שמירה
זו עברו בלא תעשה.
Mitzvat shemirah
zu avru belo ta'aseh. Not only is it a positive מצוה, mitzvah,
if you don't do it, you negate a negative. שנאמר ושמרתם את
משמרת הקודש. Shene'emar ushmartem et mishmeret hakodesh. לשון שמירה אזהרה היא. Leshon
shemirah azharah hi. Now, לשון שמירה leshon shemirah means a negative prohibition.
That's a little funny because normally לשון שמירה leshon shemirah means negative
when we say השמר לך, hishamer lecha, like guard yourself lest you
do something. Here, שמירה shemirah means do the act of guarding. It
doesn't mean, you know, protect yourself against the transgression. But anyway, what?
שומר בעלמא? Shomer be'alma?
Right. I understand. שומר בעלמא, Shomer be'alma, that's true. But there normally,
that's true, but here שמירה shemirah has the literal sense of guarding.
So to learn from it also the negative is a little interesting.
And anyway, ד Dalet he says, מצות שמירתה שהכהנים שומרים מבפנים והלויים
מבחוץ, Mitzvat shemiratah shehakohanim shomrim mibifnim vehaleviyim mibachutz, which is sort of
what we saw, the כהנים kohanim more inner and the לויים Levi'im
more on the outer. So the לויים Levi'im are on the gates,
they're in front of the gates, they're on the outside. The כהנים
kohanim are more on the inside. So this is a מצוה mitzvah
that רמב"ם Rambam says it's actually a way of showing respect, you
know. By the way, there were a lot of precious things in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. and do we know this, that was,
you know, people would rob the like pyramids or whatever, you know,
the pharaohs' graves, and even though they put all these curses on
it, I mean for some people, money is an overriding, you know,
temptation. So it's interesting that both the מפרש Mefaresh and the רמב"ם
Rambam say, of course, we wouldn't need them for the real purposes,
I mean they locked the place up. What?
From a way back history, it says also that we don't have
any פחד מאויב pachad me'oyev and things like that, so what in
terms of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash.
Right, well, I assume, but I guess if you, I understand, I
was thinking about that, but I assume that if you have actually
like an army, then a few guards isn't going to, then you
would need an army to protect against an army. But anyway, it's
interesting that they both say it's not for any sort of, you
know, pragmatic reason. And רמב"ם Rambam is the explanation most taken, that
it's a way of sort of showing respect, like guards walking around
a king's palace. So the לויים Levi'im would be on the outer,
the כהנים kohanim on the inside. Now what does it mean on
the inside? So let's keep on reading because it'll tell us more
where they were in these various rooms.
Like the לשכות lishkot of the form?
A little bit. I'll just tell you in terms of the names.
בית הניצוץ Beit HaNitzotz means a spark, so some say there was
some fire going there.
That was used for the
מזבח? mizbe'ach?
No. בית המוקד Beit HaMoked literally means the place of the bonfire,
and there there was a regularly large fire there. Some say it
was in order to constantly add fire from the to the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, because although the משנה says even though a fire comes down
from the heaven, מצוה להביא מן ההדיוט, mitzvah lehavi min hahedyot, we're
supposed to add our own fire. So some say that's why you
had a constant fire there. Others say a more pragmatic reason: כהנים
kohanim would be walking around on a cold marble floor and they
would need to warm up. And we're actually going to see that
they slept in the בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, so that's what the
בית המוקד Beit HaMoked was. בית אבטינס Beit Avtinas was the family
of כהנים kohanim that did, that made the קטורת. ketoret. So presumably
this was the room where maybe they did some
of the
manufacture. There is an
okay, if
you don't mind if I say it? Yeah, go ahead. Do they
say that for the בית הניצוץ Beit HaNitzotz some say
that the it says תוספות Tosafot says because that's where like I
guess the first rays of sun shine in. Oh, okay.
בית הניצוץ קמא דאבא
Beit HaNitzotz
Kama
d'Abba is תפארת ישראל Tiferet Yisrael says wait a minute, wait a
minute, but that's strange because
it's in the
northwest?
Yeah, well, yeah, if the sun's coming from the other
side, that's a little weird.
Although there is a debate, no, no, no, I should say there's
a debate, ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that it was
I think there's a debate בבלי Bavli ירושלמי Yerushalmi where the בית
הניצוץ Beit HaNitzotz was. No, where the בית אבטינס Beit Avtinas was.
No, everybody agrees בית הניצוץ Beit HaNitzotz was in the north. Okay,
so I don't know, anyway, it's in the north. Okay, that's a
little funny. תפארת ישראל, Tiferet Yisrael, we all know people want a
southern exposure for theory, so that's a little weird.
Yeah, and תפארת ישראל Tiferet Yisrael says because
תמיד היו בו ניצוצות של אש ממנו יכול להדליק את אש המזבח.
tamid hayu bo nitzotzot shel esh, mimenu yakhol lehadlik et esh hamizbe'ach.
Okay, so that's why some say it was the fire, although I
didn't realize that he had said that it was for the fire
of the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, most say that would be בית המוקד, Beit
HaMoked, but anyway, yeah, and then
but you know.
Okay, moving on, going on, ובבית הניצוץ היו עליות הרובים שומרים שם.
u'v'Beit HaNitzotz hayu aliyot harovim shomrim sham. In the בית הניצוץ Beit
HaNitzotz there were like steps or elevations and the רובים rovim would
watch there. Any guess what רובים rovim is? Archers. Archers. So that's
what I exactly assumed, and the רמב"ם Rambam says that, and if
you ever looked at any of those you know ancient
walls, ancient רובה קשת, roveh keshet, so you know all the classic
walls you'd have people on the top and they'd have little slits
so that the archers could shoot down, right?
And they could be protected. So that seems that that is exactly
appropriate for the idea of שומרים, shomrim, whether they actually had bows
and arrows, that's an interesting question, I don't know, but certainly they
were acting as
archers, and that also explains that the לויים Levi'im were at the
bottom watching the gates, they were on the top at the roof
and being sort of like guards on the roof or even in
an archer capacity. Now some say, which I think is less פשט
pshat because it's Aramaic, that רובים rovim is from the word רביא
ravya which means children. Yeah, I don't believe it.
I was actually going to say that, not from having looked at
this, but because you know that
רש"י Rashi says הקטעי ליה סוכלא, hakata'ei lei sukala, then רש"י Rashi
says כריביא אחתא? k'ribya achata? That they torture this child? I understand.
I think you'd have to look, I don't know if it actually
occurs in Mishnayic Hebrew,
and רובים rovim fits much better in terms of the context. Okay,
so that's what you'd have at בית הניצוץ, Beit HaNitzotz, watching from
the top, and now it doesn't actually speak about the בית אבטינס
Beit Avtinas but presumably and the מפרשים mefarshim says the same thing,
the point is the same, that the לויים Levi'im again would be
at the bottom by the gates and they would be at the
roof and at the top. So they wouldn't be watching inside the
room, what makes sense of that makes sense although I suppose they
could watch at the other gate, you know there's gates at both
ends of the room if it goes from the outside and then
into the inside, but he assumes that no, this idea that they'd
be watching from the top applies to
the
I suppose, yeah, it's a good point, but yeah, so they would
be at the top, so according to this they would be at
the top of these rooms and watching down and maybe even with
bows and arrows. Was that by both בית הניצוץ? Beit HaNitzotz? No,
no, no, he says that it's the same, he says it's the
same by everything. Now we get to the בית המוקד. Beit HaMoked.
Okay,
בית המוקד כיפה. Beit HaMoked kipa. Now the בית המוקד Beit HaMoked
had a dome on top of it. All right, now the question
here is does that mean that they would be watching from a
different place? They'd be watching from the inside, are they watching from
the top of the dome? It's not exactly clear. But anyway, by
the way, if you see the picture here by the בית המוקד,
Beit HaMoked, you see that there's a little circle in the middle
indicating a dome. Covered? Yeah, it's covered. All of these things were
covered. I mean, you're not going to have them open and have
it rain on the inside. Okay, but this presumably had a dome
top. It also was where there was a big fire, I assume.
I don't know. Anybody know the physics here, will a dome top
be better in terms of concentrating the heat? Charlie, yes, no?
Be better for getting rid of smoke.
Okay, maybe.
Anyway, okay, that would mean it would have to have been a
later building because domes didn't exist at the time that the first...
Herod. No, this is total Herod's בית המקדש. Okay, not
בית המקדש. Okay, fine, so it would have a dome top. ובית
גדול היה. u'bayit gadol hayah. And it was a big room, as
you can see it's drawn larger. Actually, if you see in the
picture, which isn't spelled out here, there were these four other chambers
that were sort of opened up into a larger central room. Okay,
so it was very large. מוקף רובדים של אבנים. mukaf rovadim shel
avanim. And it was surrounded by
steps of stone. Not exactly clear. Where the steps were, were the
steps on the inside going to a higher elevation within the inside?
Some say the steps were going from these rooms at the corner,
the steps were going up into the main room, not exactly clear.
Okay, זקני בית אב. Ziknei Beit Av. Now the זקני בית אב,
Ziknei Beit Av, which probably means which might just mean literally elders,
but presumably it actually means the people that were in charge of
the בית אב. Beit Av. The בית אב Beit Av would be
a, the group of כהנים Kohanim that was working that day. Like
there would be a משמר Mishmar which would work that week and
then each week was divided up and would work different days. שבת
Shabbat they would all work together and so
the this day's would be the בית אב Beit Av and the
ones that had sort of more, you know, administrative and authoritative positions
would be called the זקני בית אב. Ziknei Beit Av. Okay, so
they would sleep there. Now where's the there? So actually the מפרש
Mefarish says what it means is that you'd have steps going up
and then there would be little sleeping niches in the walls of
the בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, and they would sort of sleep in
there. They'd sleep up at the top in those little... you know,
sort of like you see
in... yeah, something like that. Anyway, maybe it kept them warmer also.
Anyway, that's where they would sleep.
We'll see in a minute maybe all the כהנים Kohanim slept there
of that day, but they slept presumably...
Why are they sleeping there to begin with?
Why are they sleeping? Let's take a look.
ומפתחות העזרה בידם U'maftechot HaAzara beyadam and they had the keys to
the עזרה. Azara. So they had the keys, they would be the
ones that would open it in the morning. Okay, so first of
all, you want them to sleep there because you don't want them
to have to שלעפ shlep somewhere else and come back in the
next morning, presumably they're older and it's respect
and anyway it's nice and warm there and they'll be the first
ones to open it, so they would sleep there. Now the question
I thought you were going to ask is, how could they sleep?
You're not allowed to even sit down in the עזרה. Azara. So
if you take a look at the picture here, you'll see in
the picture tiny little dots going through the middle, like a horizontal
line. Those were understood to be little dividers, you know, that would
indicate which half was on the inner half and had קדושת עזרה
Kedushat Azara and which half was the outer half and did not
have קדושת עזרה. Kedushat Azara. So they slept in the part that
did not have קדושת עזרה. Kedushat Azara. Okay, so they would sleep
there.
That's עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim we're talking about?
Yeah, or well עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael actually, this black line, right?
So which keys did they have?
The ones to open the door to עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael.
Well, what about the ones to open the door to like here
or
something?
Maybe that too, but the key as when we said the עזרה
Azara we mean עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. This is the stuff that
they are really protecting from...
so they open שער ניקנור? Sha'ar Nicanor?
That's a good question, you know, I
mean whether
whether people could gather before the, you know, before it actually opened
in the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. I'm not sure, I'd have to
see if there's a discussion about that, but I think we are
primarily talking about the keys to שער ניקנור, Sha'ar Nicanor, the keys
of עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. Okay. Alright, so they had the keys.
פרחי כהונה. Pirchei Kehunah. Now the here when we want to say
young כהנים, Kohanim, this is how we normally say it, פרחי כהונה,
Pirchei Kehunah, the young כהנים. Kohanim. איש כסותו בארץ, Ish kesuto ba'aretz,
they would have their garments on the ground next to them. Okay,
now that sounds like they actually would be sleeping there as well.
So everybody is sleeping there. So maybe the זקנים Zekenim would be
above and the פרחי כהונה Pirchei Kehunah would be below. Were they
sleeping on clothes? What? Well, they could put on their pajamas, but
they would not wear the בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. Right. Okay, לא
היו ישנים בבגדי קודש, Lo hayu yeshenim be'vigdei kodesh, they would not
sleep in the בגדי קודש, bigdei kodesh, אלא היו פושטים, Ella hayu
poshtim, they would take off their בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehunah ומניחים אותן
תחת ראשיהם, u'manichim otan tachat rasheihem, under their heads. Now this doesn't
literally mean under the head because then you're deriving benefit from בגדי
כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. It means along their, next to their head ומתכסים
בכסות עצמן, U'mitkasim bi'kesut atzman, put on their own clothes like their
pajamas, and they would sleep and they would sleep there. So in
that room that would be where... now of course what it didn't
say is: where are the שומרים? Shomrim? Yeah, everybody's sleeping there, where
are the שומרים? Shomrim? So it could be, some want to say
the פרחי כהונה Pirchei Kehunah are the שומרים, Shomrim, but then what
are they doing sleeping? So maybe it means the shift, maybe it
means their shift. Okay, or some say that the שומרים Shomrim were
on the top somehow, on the... on the dome itself. Well, maybe
the dome there's a walk-around around the dome or something. Okay, so
it's not exactly clear where the שומרים Shomrim were there, maybe on
the top. Top makes sense because you can't guard from in a
room. Alright, anyway.
One second, are these שומרים Shomrim there during the day and during
the
night or just during the night? Thank you, I meant to mention
that. So the רמב"ם Rambam, says it's מצוה כל הלילה. mitzvah kol
halaila. So the רמב"ם Rambam implies that it's only a nighttime מצוה.
mitzvah. The מפרש Mefarish and others say that it was a מצוה
mitzvah day and night. So there actually is a debate whether it
occurred day and night. You would actually think that according to the
רמב"ם, Rambam if it's about כבוד, kavod, then you want people to
see it and you want it during the day as well. Even
more so in the day. I know, but you would want people
to see guards walking around, you know, because the רמב"ם says it's
about כבוד. kavod. But the רמב"ם limits it to night; others say
day and night. Now, אירע קרי לאחד מהם, ira keri leachad mehem,
if one of them had a nocturnal emission, right, had a seminal
emission at night. So now he's טמא. tamei. He's a בעל קרי.
ba'al keri. You're not allowed in the עזרה. azara. What's he going
to do? So he has to, he can leave, but he can't
leave going through the עזרה azara or cross into the עזרה. azara.
Good thing he's sleeping on the outer half. So what's he going
to do about this? Okay. יוצא והולך לו במסיבה ההולכת לו תחת
הבירה. yotzei veholech lo bimsiba haholechet lo tachat habira. He goes in
the walk-around or in the tunnel that goes under something, do they
have a diagram of a spiral staircase? No. Something like that. Again,
some of these terms are not exactly clear, but some type of
stairs or tunnel that goes underneath the בירה. bira. Some say the
בירה bira means the entire בית המקדש. Question of exactly what that
word refers to, but some say it just means a particular room,
some say it's a particular space in the
בית המקדש.
These four compartments, בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, the one on the bottom
right is, what does it say?
ירידה לבית הטבילה. yeridah lebeit hatvilah. Right. So basically that's it. There
would be some type of, some type of a tunnel from that
place to get, you know. Now again, what does תחת הבירה tachat
habira mean? Presumably it means some space, either the whole בית המקדש
or some area in the בית המקדש. But where was the בית
הטבילה? beit hatvilah?
So, you know there are those מקואות mikvahs that they uncovered, right,
outside the walls when you go down to the southern wall?
Right. Oh yeah?
I hadn't remembered that. Okay, so that probably is where we're talking
about. Okay.
Oh, מקואות mikvahs on the north.
Yeah, he'd have to go all the way across.
I saw it on the southern wall. Well, there are probably, the
מקואות mikvahs for the, at the south were probably for the people
who were just coming in the בית המקדש.
But if they went underground, there probably was a מקוה mikvah there,
too.
Okay, let's just finish this point.
So you're saying where's this מקוה?
mikvah? I don't know. So let's keep on reading, somewhere,
where the tunnel got to.
There's one in the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. What? There's one in
the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim right past, right after.
So it says מקוה mikvah by the לשכת מצורעים. lishkat metzoraim. That's
interesting. Okay, anyway, let's just finish this point and we'll continue with
this tomorrow. ומדורה הייתה שם. umedura hayata sham. And נרות דולקים מכאן
ומכאן. nerot dolkim mikan umikan. You'd have candles lit along the tunnel.
Somebody would have to go every, probably every day and relight the
candles, right? Or maybe, maybe there'd be candles and he would light
them as he was going. Makes more sense. Anyway, עד שהוא מגיע
לבית הטבילה ad shehu magia lebeit hatvilah until he got to the
actual מקוה. mikvah. ומדורה הייתה שם umedura hayata sham and there was
a fire by the מקוה mikvah cause, you know, he's got to
go in the early morning to the מקוה. mikvah. You want to
make sure that people don't hesitate, so you got to keep it
nice and warm. ובית הכסא של כבוד. ubeit hakise shel kavod. And
there was an honorable bathroom. Now, toilet. Why did, now why did
you have a toilet there all together? I mean, you could say
people need it, but fine, why put it right there? So one
of the reasons is because if he needs to urinate and he
doesn't, and he still has some semen inside of him, and then
when he urinates again and the semen comes out, he'll become טמא
tamei again. So you want to make sure that he takes care
of all of that before going to the מקוה mikvah so he's
טהור. tahor.
Okay. But also, you know, after you defecate, don't you have to
do a whole טבילה tvilah anyway?
Yeah, but that's, so they might, fine, maybe, could be, could be.
I mean, yeah, there were no other bathrooms, no bathrooms in the
whole,
I don't know if there were no others, but
this, here's one in the, and this, זה היה כבודו ze haya
kevodo and this was the way in which it gave honor, or
it was a respectful, maybe is the better way of, a respectful
bathroom. מצאו נעול יודע שיש שם אדם. matzu naul yodea sheyesh sham
adam. פתוח בידוע שאין שם אדם. patuach beyadua she'ein sham adam. People
would know, if it's locked, somebody is there, and if it's unlocked,
somebody isn't there, so people would not, you know, walk in on
somebody else using the bathroom and it would be a sign to
show respect. Why do they have to tell us this?
Common sense? Presumably the fact they had to tell you shows it
was not always the practice. Often people would anyway go to the
bathroom in the woods. So first of all, they're showing that you
have it in a
respected place and that people would pay attention to the convention. Look,
we all know, I'm sure in our lives, I'm sure with my
kids, whatever, sometimes you walk into a bathroom and somebody didn't bother
locking the door, right? So it's also showing you that people were
מקפיד makpid to keep to this convention.
There weren't so many bathrooms then.
That's true. Okay. All right, so we will finish this משנה and
continue the גמרא on this tomorrow. Okay.